Hello friends, today I will tell you
about loan insurance. If you have taken a
loan from a bank, what is the insurance for that loan?
What is loan insurance and why do we need it?
You can understand
why I made this video by watching this picture. See,
whenever you know who takes the loan in a family, the
bread earner takes it. In these cases, something goes wrong and the
bread earner dies, then the
burden of repaying the loan is very heavy on the family.
Loan insurance is taken for their protection. If, let's say, the person
who took the loan has some
mishap, then their loan will be
fulfilled through the loan insurance policy and so that the family will
not face any financial burden. Now
today we will understand about it,
what is its premium, who
can take it, and all the basic details that you
need. We will
read about it. First of all, understand that the policy
covers the loan amount. If
anything goes wrong with the borrower, then the
insurance company will take care of the entire loan
repayment.  It does this and gets NOC
from the bank. Family members are covered under this.
Critical illness means the
stage in which the breadwinner will not be able to do anything now,
like permanent disability of this
type or debt insurance. Only these
two things are covered under this. This thing is
not covered under this that if you lose your job due to
any reason, then it is not covered under it.
It does not provide any policy.
Now under this
you can put both the applicants in insurance
or you can put one of them in insurance
or you can put them according to the proportionate sharing of both, that is,
if this applicant expires, then 50% loan will be
repaid. If the applicant expires, then 50
%
loan will be repaid. In this way, you
can cover both of them. The tenure of the insurance policy will
remain equal to the loan tenure of the policy. Now there are some things under this, the
premium of the insurance
mainly depends on four factors. Loan
amount: If the loan amount is high, then the
premium will be high. Repayment period: If
If the age is high then the premium will be high. If the age of the person or the age of the person is high then the
premium will be high. If there are some health
issues then if they are high then the
premium will be high. The
best benefit in this is that if you take this policy
then you also get the benefit of ATC. So
you can see it as a benefit from this angle also.
Suicide is
not covered under this. Suppose if someone commits suicide then it is
not covered. There are some policies
which do not cover suicide for one year
but if it happens after one year then when you
read the policy document then
you will see all these things in detail.
Now the most important thing in this
which is most prevalent in today's date is
mis-selling of insurance by the bank.
What happens is that you
take insurance from the bank, you go to get a loan, the bank
manager says that you will be insured
but instead of calling your insurance as loan protection
insurance, he makes a normal insurance
due to which the
bank gets more commission. Meaning you took a loan and
your insurance is also done but the
insurance is not for your loan but for a normal
insurance policy.  He got it
issued for you and it has
nothing to do with loan coverage and especially this is happening a
lot in State Bank of India. So for this, let's
assume that
you have taken a policy from any bank, public sector
bank or private sector bank.
The day the policy comes to you,
read it carefully
because you have 14 days to
cancel the policy. You get the
full premium back under it.
Read the policy and see whether they have
covered the entire loan amount or not. Is there
anything missing regarding the loan amount? Will the
insurance company make the payment or not?
Read all the policy documents very carefully. Only if you are satisfied,
accept it, otherwise decline it within 14 days.
Now, one important
thing is that the branch manager will generally
try to sell you a policy in which the bank
gets a higher commission, not the policy
for loan insurance. So, pay
special attention to this thing. Secondly, check whether the main
applicant is covered or not because the
main applicant means the bread earner.
It covered the applicant
but did not cover the main applicant. Let's assume that
both the husband and wife
are applicants. The insurance policy
covers the wife but does
not cover the husband who is the main earner and something happens to him. It turns out that the
insurance policy
itself is meaningless. Keep this in mind
and remember one thing,
always choose regular premium instead of one-time premium.
Regular premium is because
suppose you close your loan account early, then
you have to
pay premium for the same number of years for which your loan was in force. Otherwise, what will happen
if you pay one-time
premium and you
close the loan in half the tenure, then your premium of half the tenure goes
waste. So, no matter which
policy you have, you should always choose regular premium
and the
important point is firstly whether the policy has
loan protection cover or
not. Secondly, the policy does
not require loan protection policy. You can buy it from the same bank from
where you took the loan. You can take loan
policy from any bank or any
insurance company and
after the loan is over,  You can also take it.
It is not that
you can get your insurance anytime before or within a month of the loan being activated.
I have already told you this about the production society and not the grave. And
yes, let's assume you don't want to get into all this hassle. So,
I would make a simple and strong
recommendation that you take out term insurance for whatever loan amount you have.
Term insurance is very less in cost. For example, let's
assume I have got my
term insurance from two places.
One is from ICICI Bank for Rs.
50 lakh, whose installment is Rs. 6,000, and the other is
from HDFC Life Insurance for Rs. 70 lakh, whose installment is Rs.
11,000. So, get yourself insured for at least Rs. 1 crore. If
something goes wrong, at
least your family doesn't have to travel.
Friends, we provide personal loans and
business loans all over India. If
any of your friends or relatives need a personal loan or
business loan, you can contact us.
We pay a commission of up to Rs. 2 per cent.
For the policies given by us,
I made a video on it,
you can watch it by clicking above. I have
covered in that video that
if any policy is given to you by mistake by someone and
then you have 15 days from the date of receipt of the document to
put it in free lookup.
If before 15 days you
call the customer care and tell them that
you do not want this policy, then you get the full
premium returned. There is
no penalty of any kind in it.
To watch that video in full detail,
click on the button given above.
Thank you and